A Guide to the Papers of Oscar A. Thorup, Jr., 1956-1997
Historical Collections, Claude Moore Health Sciences Library
- Memo from Dr. Moreland, Director of the Vivarium, to Oscar A. Thorup, [1963], T memo (Box-folder 004-016)
  Concerns the history and current status of Congressional bills to regulate animal experimentation.
- Summer Fellowship application, guidelines, [ND,1963?], TD (Box-folder 004-017)
  Medical Student Research Fellowship Program
- Summer Fellowship for 1963, 1963, TL (Box-folder 004-018)
- Correspondence: from U.S. Senator Winston L. Prouty to [Oscar A. Thorup], [March 1963], TDS copy (Box-folder 004-019)
  Concerns the humane treatment of animals used in research.
- Correspondence: from to Oscar A. Thorup to Senator Lister Hill, March 4, 1963, TL, TL copy, AL (Box-folder 004-020)
  Thorup writes in opposition to the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Oscar A. Thorup to Dietrich Bodenstein, March 6, 1963, TL copy (Box-folder 004-021)
- Correspondence: from Senator A. Willis Roberson to Oscar A. Thorup, March 7, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-022)
  Robertson thanks Thorup for his letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Jennings Randolph to William Parson, March 7, 1963, TL copy (Box-folder 004-023)
  Robertson thanks Parson for his letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Jennings Randolph to Oscar A. Thorup, S. 1041 88th Congress, 1st Session, A Bill, March 7-11, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-024)
  Robertson thanks Thorup for his letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments and gives a copy of the bill as well as his remarks.
- Correspondence: from Robert W. Barclay to Oscar A. Thorup, March 8, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-025)
  Barclay thanks Thorup for his letter regarding the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Harry F. Byrd to Oscar A. Thorup, March 8, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-026)
  Byrd notes Thorup's letter.
- Correspondence: from Representative Howard W. Smith to Oscar A. Thorup, March 8, 1963, TL (Box-folder 004-027)
  Smith informs Thorup that he thinks Thorup doesn't have to worry much about the bill concerning the use of animals in laboratory experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Claiborne Pell to Oscar A. Thorup, March 12, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-028)
  Pell thanks Thorup for his letter regarding the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Ralph Yarborough to Oscar A. Thorup, March 13, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-029)
  Yarborough thanks Thorup for his letter regarding the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Harrison A. Williams to Oscar A. Thorup, March 15, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-030)
  Williams thanks Thorup for his letter regarding the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Jacob K. Javits to Oscar A. Thorup, March 20, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-031)
  Javits thanks Thorup for his letter regarding the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Oscar A. Thorup to Jennings Randolph, March 25, 1963, TL copy (Box-folder 004-032)
  Thorup explains his objection to the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Len B. Jordan to Oscar A. Thorup, March 26, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-033)
  Jordan responds to Thorup's letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from Senator Edward M. Kennedy to Oscar A. Thorup, from Senator Edward M. Kennedy to William Parson, March 27, 1963, TLS, TL copy (Box-folder 004-034)
  Kennedy thanks Thorup for his letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Correspondence: from John G. Tower to Oscar A. Thorup, April 4, 1963, TLS (Box-folder 004-035)
  Tower thanks Thorup for his letter about the bill concerning treatment of animals used in experiments.
- Conference on Medical Education, School of Medicine, University of Virginia, January 3-4, 1964, AN, TD mimeographed, brochure, graphs, program (Box-folder 004-036)
  The conference was held at Williamsburg, Virginia. Includes graphs for number of publications, as well as residents, interns, fellows, and research associates for 1953 through 1963. Also standing committees for persons at risk and patterns of staffing for 1953 through 1963. The agenda for the meeting in Williamsburg and an extensive program is included. The program's index has entries for objectives of predoctoral medical education, internship and residency program, medical colleges with the highest percentage of graduation in full-time teaching and/or research 1935-1950, proportions of 1934-58 physician graduates holding full-time faculty appointments, July 1960, percentage of graduates who specialize, percentage of national classes choosing specialties, medical college admission test mean scores-entering classes for UVa 1962-63, mean college admission test group frequency distribution of scores for entering classes and all applicants for UVa 1962-63, mean scores of medical students on medical colleges admission test by region and for 14 public and 9 private schools in the state 1958-59, medical college admission test mean scores for entering students and applicants at UVa compared to national mean scores of accepted applicants 1952-63, curriculum evaluation and revision, primary areas of concern, proposals.
- Hospital Utilization Committee, April 29, 1964-November 15, 1965, TL (Box-folder 004-037)
  Includes report and meeting minutes.
- Summer exchange: Cork, Ireland for 1964, 1964, TL, AL (Box-folder 004-038)
- Summer exchange: London for 1964, 1964, TL, AL (Box-folder 004-039)
- Summer exchange: Malmo, Sweden for 1964, 1964, TL (Box-folder 004-040)
- Summer exchange: Manchester for 1964, 1963-1964, TL, AL (Box-folder 004-041)
- Summer exchange: Newcastle upon Tyne for 1964, 1963-1964, TL, AN (Box-folder 004-042)
- Summer exchange: Ormskirk, England for 1964, 1964, AL (Box-folder 004-043)
- Summer exchange: Oslo for 1964, 1963-1964, TL, AN (Box-folder 004-044)
- Summer exchange: Sussex for 1964, 1964, AL (Box-folder 004-045)
- Summer exchange: Michael Patterson, 1964, [1964], photos (Box-folder 004-046)
- University wide self study, 1965, 1955-1964, TD, TL, AN (Box-folder 005-001)
- Summer exchange: London for 1965, 1965, TL (Box-folder 005-002)
- Summer exchange: Manchester for 1965, 1964-1965, TL (Box-folder 005-003)
- Summer exchange: Preston, Lancashire, England for 1965, 1965, TL, AL (Box-folder 005-004)
- Examination of the Patient, Second Year Students, 1965, TD (Box-folder 005-005)
- The Towers CCF (Continuing Care Facility), October 1, 1970, TD (Box-folder 005-006)
  Includes floor plans, medical services, objectives.
- Correspondence and travel notes: concerning visit to Finland, Norway, and Sweden, July-December 1972, TL, TD, AD (Box-folder 005-007)
- Physical Diagnosis, 1975-76, TD, AN (Box-folder 005-008)
- Leavell and Thorup's Fundamentals of Clinical Hematology, 1979-81, TD, TL, AN (Box-folder 005-009)
  Includes authors, royalties, author pay, letters from Oscar Thorup and Roberta Kangilaski, Saunders Company, chapter responsibilities.
- Correspondence: to Oscar Thorup, April 30, 1980, ALS, envelope (Box-folder 005-010)
- Medical Center Hour: The New Anti-vivisectionism: Implications of the "Animal Rights" Movement, November 19, 1980, flyer (Box-folder 005-011)
  Moderated by Oscar A. Thorup.
- UVa School of Medicine Class of 1946 fund and 35th reunion, January 21, 1981, TD, TL, AL (Box-folder 005-012)
  Correspondents include Oscar Thorup, Sam Graham, Arthur Ebbert, and Barbara Henderson. Information on the 1946 Medical Class Loan Fund is included.
- UVa School of Medicine Class of 1946 fund and 40th reunion, 1985-86, TD, TL, AL (Box-folder 005-013)
  Correspondents include Oscar Thorup, Sam Graham, and Dennis P. McCarty.
- Correspondence: Donald Z. Feinstein of the American Society of Hematology to Oscar Thorup, January 19, 1990, TL (Box-folder 005-014)
- Correspondence: Arthur Ebbert to Barby and Oscar Thorup, September 23, 1990, AL (Box-folder 005-015)
- History of the Health Sciences lecture Series by Oscar A. Thorup "Medicine and Thomas Jefferson," November 14, 1990, brochures (Box-folder 005-016)
- UVa Class of 1944 50th reunion, May 17-18, 1994, TD, certificate, name badge (Box-folder 005-017)
  The certificate declares Oscar Andreas Thorup a member of the Thomas Jefferson Society of Alumni for his 50 years of service.
- Special Libraries: American Philosophical Society, 1988, TD, TL, AN (Box-folder 006-001)
  For purposes of research on Thomas Jefferson.
- Special Libraries: Bibliotheque Nationale, 1988, TL, AN (Box-folder 006-002)
- Special Libraries: Bodleian Library, 1988, TD, TL, AN; reprints (Box-folder 006-003)
- Special Libraries: British Library, 1988, TL, photo (Box-folder 006-004)
- Special Libraries: Massachusetts Historical Society, 1988, TD, TL, AN (Box-folder 006-005)
- Special Libraries: National Archives, March 10, 1997, TD, TL with AN (Box-folder 006-006)
  Includes article about the National Archives partnering with Thomas Jefferson University to broadly distribute educational packets on Jefferson.
- Special Libraries: Massachusetts Historical Society, 1988, TL, AN (Box-folder 006-007)
- Eastern Virginia Medical School and William and Mary, February 10, 1978, TL, TD, AN (Box-folder 006-008)
  Includes letter from Gerald H. Holman to Oscar A. Thorup and copies of letters and documents related to Jefferson and Eastern Virginia and William and Mary.
- "Thomas Jefferson Writes to His 11-Year Old Daughter" Pediatrics, Vol. 51, No. 4, April 1973, journal clipping, AN (Box-folder 006-009)
  Jefferson gives his daughter a daily schedule in a letter dated November 28, 1783.
- Correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and Thomas Mann Randolph Jr., 1787, AL copy with transcript (Box-folder 006-010)
  Includes Jefferson's thoughts on education.
- Correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and P. and C. Roche, June 1807, AL copy (Box-folder 006-011)
  Concerns education.
- Correspondence from Thomas Jefferson concerning his grandson, Thomas Jefferson Randolph, 1807-1808, AL copies, transcripts (Box-folder 006-012)
  Jefferson takes part in his grandson's education.
- Correspondence from Casper Wistar to Thomas Jefferson, 1806, 1813, 1815,1817, AL copies, transcripts (Box-folder 006-013)
- "A Bill for Establishing a System of Public Education, 1818, copy of the bill (Box-folder 006-014)
  Sent to Cabell, passed February 21, 1818, to provide citizens of the commonwealth a primary grade of education at the common expense.
- Correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and Jos. C. Cabell [Joseph Carrington Cabell], 1817-1825, AL copies, transcripts (Box-folder 006-015)
  Related to education.
- Correspondence from Thomas Jefferson and [James] Madison, May 16, 1824, AL copy, transcript (Box-folder 006-016)
- Correspondence from Thomas Jefferson and J Breckenridge, December 22, 1824, AL copy, transcript (Box-folder 006-017)
- Correspondence between Thomas Jefferson and [James] Barbour and [Littleton Waller] Tazewell, 1824-1825, AL copies, transcripts (Box-folder 006-018)
- Correspondence from Thomas Jefferson and [Hutchins G.?] Burton, March 2, 1825, AL copy, transcript (Box-folder 006-019)
- Correspondence from Thomas Jefferson and JB [J Breckenridge?], April 16, 1825, AL copy, transcript (Box-folder 006-020)
- University of Virginia Board of Visitors Comment on the Honor System, October 3, 1825, TL, AN, copy (Box-folder 006-021)
- Kain, Charles, "History of Smallpox and Its Prevention" American Journal of Diseases of Children, vol. 106, December 1963, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-022)
- Koch, Adrienne, "The Philosophy of Thomas Jefferson": Chapters 7, 8, 9, 10, 12, 1957, copy of book chapters (Box-folder 006-023)
- Leavell, Byrd S., "Thomas Jefferson, Robley Dunglison and the Founding of the University of Virginia School of Medicine, "[1978?], TD (Box-folder 006-024)
- Leavell, Byrd S., "Thomas Jefferson and Smallpox Vaccination: Trans. Am. Can. C., [1980?], copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-025)
- Malone, Dumas, "Jefferson and the Rights of Man," p 16-17, 1951, copy of book excerpt (Box-folder 006-026)
- Martin, Henry A., "Jefferson As a Vaccinator" North Carolina Medical Journal, Vol. 7, No. 1, January 1881, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-027)
- Mayer, Jean, "A Jeffersonian Ideal" The Chronicle [of Higher Education?], [1976], copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-028)
- Moll, Wilhelm, "Medicine,, From the First, Was Part of UVa Teaching" The Daily Progress, April 13, 1969, copy of newspaper article (Box-folder 006-029)
- Moore, Thomas C., "Medical Education at America's First University" Journal of Medical Education, Vol. 44, April 1969, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-030)
- Oliver, John W., "Thomas Jefferson - Scientist: Scientific Monthly, Vol. 56, No. 5, 1943, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-031)
- Philo Justitiae, "Sketch of the Life of Benjamin Waterhouse M.D." The Polyanthos, Vol. 2, May 1806, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-032)
- Radbill, Samuel X., "Dr. Robley Dunglison and Jefferson" Trans. Stud. Coll. Physicians Phila. Vol. 27, No. 1, July 1959, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-033)
- Radbill, Samuel X., "Thomas Jefferson and the Doctors" Trans. Stud. Coll. Physicians Phila. Vol. 37, No. 2, October 1969, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-034)
- Rosen, George, "Political Order and Human Health in Jeffersonian Thought" Amer. Assoc. of the History of Med., Baltimore, May 3, 1951, copy of journal article, TL, AN (Box-folder 006-035)
  Also includes a letter from Joseph Fletcher to Oscar Thorup, August 28, 1988 and notes by Thorup on the talk.
- Schullian, Dorothy M., "Notes and Events: The Anonymous Publications of Benjamin Waterhouse" J. Hist. Med., April 1958, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-036)
- Shield, James Asa, "Jefferson's School of Medicine at the College of William and Mary in Virginia" published in Virginia Medical Monthly Vol. 95, February 1968, TD with AN (Box-folder 006-037)
- Shield, James Asa, "Jefferson's School of Medicine at the College of William and Mary in Virginia" Virginia Medical Monthly Vol. 95, February 1968, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-038)
- Spratt, John S., "Thomas Jefferseon: The Scholarly Politician and His Influence on Medicine" Southern Medical Journal Vol. 69, No. 3, March 1976, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-039)
- Thould, A.K., "The health of Thomas Jefferson (1743-1826) J. of the Royal College of Physicians of London Vol. 23, No. 1, January 1, 1989, incomplete copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-040)
- Thurm, Richard H., "Dr. Benjamin Waterhouse and the Boston Marine Hospital: Annals of Internal Medicine Vol. 76, 1972, copy of journal article (Box-folder 006-041)
- Trent, Josiah Charles, "Benjamin Waterhouse (1754-1846)" J. Hist. Med, July 1946, copy of journal article with AN (Box-folder 006-042)